It's a great time to be a molecular biologist. (Laughter)
إنه وقت عظيم لأكون متخصصة أحياء جزيئية
Reading and writing DNA code is getting easier
قراءة و كتابة شفرات الحمض النووي أصبح أسهل
and cheaper.
و منخفض التكلفة
By the end of this year, we'll be able to sequence
في نهاية هذه السنة سنكون قادرين على سلسلة
the three million bits of information
الثلاثة ملايين بت من المعلومات
in your genome in less than a day
في الجينوم الخاص بك في أقل من يوم
and for less than 1,000 euros.
وبأقل من ألف يورو
Biotech is probably the most powerful
البيوتكنلوجيا ربما هي الأقوى
and the fastest-growing technology sector.
وأسرع مجال تكنلوجي سرعة في النمو
It has the power, potentially,
لديها القوة
to replace our fossil fuels,
لتحل محل الوقود الأحفوري
to revolutionize medicine,
لتحدث ثورة في الطب
and to touch every aspect of our daily lives.
وتتعرض لكل جانب من الحياة اليومية
So who gets to do it?
من سيقوم بذلك؟
I think we'd all be pretty comfortable with
أعتقد أننا سنكون كلنا مرتاحين مع
this guy doing it.
هذا الشخص الذي يقوم بها
But what about
و لكن ماذا بخصوص
that guy? (Laughter)
هذا الشخص؟ (ضحك )
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In 2009, I first heard about DIYbio.
في سنة 2009 سمعت لأول مرة ب DIYbio
It's a movement that -- it advocates making biotechnology
إنها حركة تدعو للقيام بالبيوتكنلوجيا
accessible to everyone,
متاحة للجميع
not just scientists and people in government labs.
ليس فقط للعلماء والعاملين في المختبرات الحكومية
The idea is that if you open up the science
الفكرة تتمثل في فتح العلم
and you allow diverse groups to participate,
و السماح للعديد من المجموعات بالمشاركة
it could really stimulate innovation.
قد تقوم حقيقة بتحفيز الإبتكار
Putting technology in the hands of the end user
وضع التكنلوجيا بين أيادي المستخدم العادي
is usually a good idea because they've got the best idea
عموما فكرة جيدة لأنهم إمتلكوا أفضل الأفكار
of what their needs are.
لماهية احتياجاتهم
And here's this really sophisticated technology
و ها هي ذي التكنلوجيا المعقدة
coming down the road, all these associated
قادمة في الطريق، كلها مصحوبة ب
social, moral, ethical questions,
أسئلة اجتماعية و أخلاقية ،
and we scientists are just lousy at explaining to the public
و نحن العلماء فاشلون في الشرح لعامة الناس
just exactly what it is we're doing in those labs.
تحديدا ما نقوم به في المختبرات
So wouldn't it be nice
كم سيكون جميلا
if there was a place in your local neighborhood
لو وجد مكان في حيك
where you could go and learn about this stuff,
حيث يمكن لك الذهاب وتعلم هذه الأشياء
do it hands-on?
القيام بالتدريب العملي على ذلك
I thought so.
فكرت بذلك
So, three years ago, I got together
قبل ثلاثة أعوام مضت ، اجتمعت
with some friends of mine who had similar aspirations
مع بعض أصدقائي الذين يملكون نفس التطلعات
and we founded Genspace.
و أسسنا Genspace
It's a nonprofit, a community biotech lab
هي منظمة غير ربحية لمختبرات البيوتكنلوجيا
in Brooklyn, New York,
في بروكلين ، نيويورك
and the idea was people could come,
والفكرة كانت أن الجمهور يمكنه الحضور
they could take classes and putter around in the lab
وأخذ دروس والتجول داخل المختبر
in a very open, friendly atmosphere.
في جو متفتح وحميمي
None of my previous experience prepared me
وليس لدي خبرة سابقة حضّرتني
for what came next. Can you guess?
لما سيأتي لاحقا . هل يمكنكم التخمين ؟
The press started calling us.
الصحافة بدأت بالإتصال بنا
And the more we talked about how great it was to increase
وكلما تحدثنا عن مدى روعتها للإرتقاء
science literacy, the more they wanted to talk
بمحو الأمية العلمية ، كلما حاولوا التحدث
about us creating the next Frankenstein,
معنا حول خلق فرانكنشتاين القادم
and as a result, for the next six months,
و كنتيجة لذلك، للستة شهور القادمة
when you Googled my name,
عندما تبحث عن اسمي في غوغل
instead of getting my scientific papers, you got this.
عوض أن تجد أبحاثي العلمية ، ستجد هذا
["Am I a biohazard?"]
"هل أنا خطر بيولوجي ؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It was pretty depressing.
لقد كان محبطا.
The only thing that got us through that period
الشيء الوحيد الذي جعلنا نتخطى هذه الفكرة
was that we knew that all over the world,
هو كوننا نعرف في كل أرجاء العالم،
there were other people that were trying to do
هنالك أشخاص يحاولون القيام
the same thing that we were.
بنفس الأشياء التي نقوم بها
They were opening biohacker spaces, and some of them
كانوا يفتحون مساحات البيوهاكر، والبعض منهم
were facing much greater challenges than we did,
كانوا يواجهون تحديات أعظم مما واجهنا،
more regulations, less resources.
قوانين أكثر و موارد أقل
But now, three years later, here's where we stand.
أما الآن ، بعد ثلاث سنين ، ها نحن ذا.
It's a vibrant, global community of hackerspaces,
انه مجتمع عالمي وحيوي من الهاكرسبايسز،
and this is just the beginning.
وهذه مجرد بداية .
These are some of the biggest ones,
هاهي بعض من أكبرها،
and there are others opening every day.
وهناك أخرى تفتح يوميا .
There's one probably going to open up in Moscow,
هناك واحد سيفتتح في موسكو،
one in South Korea,
وآخر في كوريا الجنوبية ،
and the cool thing is they each have their own
والشيء الممتع هو كل منها تمتلك
individual flavor
ذوقها الفريد
that grew out of the community they came out of.
الذي يكبر من المجتمع النابع منها
Let me take you on a little tour.
دعني أخذكم في جولة قصيرة.
Biohackers work alone.
ال Biohackers يعملون بمفردهم.
We work in groups,
إننا نعمل في مجموعات،
in big cities — (Laughter) —
في كبرى المدن -( ضحك )-
and in small villages.
وفي القرى الصغيرة .
We reverse engineer lab equipment.
نغيّر المعدات المخبرية للمهندس
We genetically engineer bacteria.
نحن ندرس البكتيريا جينيا
We hack hardware,
ونخترق الأجهزة،
software,
البرمجيات،
wetware,
الويتوار،
and, of course, the code of life.
وطبعا، شفرة الحياة.
We like to build things.
نود بناء الأشياء.
Then we like to take things apart.
ثم نحب أن نأخذ الأمور على حدى.
We make things grow.
نحن نجعل الأمور تنمو.
We make things glow.
ونحن جعل الأمور تتوهج.
And we make cells dance.
ونحن نجعل الخلايا ترقص.
The spirit of these labs, it's open, it's positive,
سمة هذه المعامل، أنها مفتوحة، وأنها إيجابية،
but, you know, sometimes when people think of us,
ولكن، كما تعلمون، في بعض الأحيان عندما يفكر الناس فينا،
the first thing that comes to mind is bio-safety,
الشيء الأول الذي يتبادر إلى الذهن هو السلامة الأحيائية،
bio-security, all the dark side stuff.
الأمن البيولوجي، جميع الأشياء المظلمة الجانب.
I'm not going to minimize those concerns.
لست عازمة على التقليل من هذه المخاوف.
Any powerful technology is inherently dual use,
أي تقنية قوية هي عادة مزدوجة الاستخدام،
and, you know, you get something like
وكما تعلمون، يمكنك الحصول على شيء مثل
synthetic biology, nanobiotechnology,
البيولوجيا الاصطناعية، النانوية،
it really compels you, you have to look at both
حقاً أنها تجبرك، يتوجب عليك النظر إلى كل من
the amateur groups but also the professional groups,
مجموعات الهواة ولكن أيضا المجموعات المهنية،
because they have better infrastructure,
لأنها تملك بنية أساسية أفضل،
they have better facilities,
لديهم مرافق أفضل،
and they have access to pathogens.
وأنهم يستطيعون الوصول إلى مسببات الأمراض.
So the United Nations did just that, and they recently
الأمم المتحدة قامت بذلك، و مؤخرا
issued a report on this whole area,
أصدرت تقريرا عن هذه المنطقة كلها،
and what they concluded was the power of this technology
و ما خلصوا اليه أن قوة هذه التكنولوجيا
for positive was much greater than the risk for negative,
الإيجابية أكبر بكثير من الخطر السلبي،
and they even looked specifically at the DIYbio community,
وحتى بدت على وجه التحديد في المجتمع DIYbio،
and they noted, not surprisingly, that the press
ولاحظوا، ليس من المستغرب، أن الصحافة
had a tendency to consistently overestimate our capabilities
قد تميل إلى المبالغة في تقدير قدراتنا
and underestimate our ethics.
والتقليل من اخلاقنا.
As a matter of fact, DIY people from all over the world,
في واقع الأمر، مجتمع DIY من جميع أنحاء العالم،
America, Europe, got together last year,
أمريكا، وأوروبا، إجتمعنا معا في العام الماضي،
and we hammered out a common code of ethics.
وتمكنا من التوصل الى ميثاق مشترك للأخلاقيات.
That's a lot more than conventional science has done.
وهذا أكثر بكثير مما قام به العلوم التقليدية.
Now, we follow state and local regulations.
الآن، ونحن نتقيد بالقوانين المحلية.
We dispose of our waste properly, we follow
علينا التخلص من النفايات بشكل صحيح، ونحن نتقيد
safety procedures, we don't work with pathogens.
بإجراءات السلامة، نحن لا نعمل مع مسببات الأمراض.
You know, if you're working with a pathogen,
أنت تعرف، إذا كنت تعمل مع مسببات المرض،
you're not part of the biohacker community,
فأنت لست جزءا من المجتمع البيوهاكير،
you're part of the bioterrorist community, I'm sorry.
اذا كنت جزءا من مجتمع الإرهاب البيولوجي، لست جزءا.
And sometimes people ask me,
وأحيانا يسألني الناس،
"Well, what about an accident?"
"حسنا، ماذا إن تعلّق الأمر بحادث؟"
Well, working with the safe organisms that we normally
حسنا، العمل مع الكائنات الآمنة التي نحن عادة
work with, the chance of an accident happening
نعمل معها، وفرصة حدوث حادث
with somebody accidentally creating, like,
مع شخص ما صنع خطئا مثل،
some sort of superbug,
نوعا من الحشرات العملاقة،
that's literally about as probable as a snowstorm
هذا تقريبا كفرضية حدوث عاصفة ثلجية
in the middle of the Sahara Desert.
في وسط الصحراء الكبرى.
Now, it could happen,
الآن، يمكن أن يحدث،
but I'm not going to plan my life around it.
ولكن أنا لن أخطط لحياتي في هذا النطاق.
I've actually chosen to take a different kind of risk.
لقد اخترت خوض نوع مختلف من المخاطر.
I signed up for something called the Personal Genome Project.
حتى أنني وقعت لما يسمى "مشروع الجينوم البشري الشخصي".
It's a study at Harvard where, at the end of the study,
هي دراسة في جامعة هارفارد حيث، في نهاية الدراسة،
they're going to take my entire genomic sequence,
سيتخذون تسلسل الجينوم الخاص بي بأكمله،
all of my medical information, and my identity,
جميع المعلومات الطبية الخاصة بي، وهويتي،
and they're going to post it online for everyone to see.
وسينشرون ذلك على الإنترنت للجميع حتى يطلعون عليه.
There were a lot of risks involved that they talked about
كان هناك الكثير من المخاطر التي تحدثنا عنها
during the informed consent portion.
أثناء فترة القبول.
The one I liked the best is,
الأفضل بالنسبة لي هو،
someone could download my sequence, go back to the lab,
شخص ما سيتمكن من تحميل تسلسلي الجبني، والعودة إلى المختبر،
synthesize some fake Ellen DNA,
توليف بعض الحمض النووي لإلين الوهمية،
and plant it at a crime scene. (Laughter)
وزرعه في مسرح جريمة. (ضحك)
But like DIYbio, the positive outcomes and
ولكن مثل DIYbio،النتائج الإيجابية و
the potential for good for a study like that
الإمكانات الجيدة لدراسة مثل هذه
far outweighs the risk.
تفوق بكثير المخاطر.
Now, you might be asking yourself,
الآن، يمكن أن تسأل نفسك،
"Well, you know, what would I do in a biolab?"
"حسنا، تعلمون، ماذا أفعل في المختبر البيولوجي؟"
Well, it wasn't that long ago we were asking, "Well,
حسنا، ليس فترة طويلة كنا نتسائل، "حسنا،
what would anyone do with a personal computer?"
ماذا يمكن لأي شخص أن يفعل بكمبيوتر شخصي؟ "
So this stuff is just beginning.
لذا هو مجرد بداية لهذا الأمر.
We're only seeing just the tip of the DNA iceberg.
نحن نشهد فقط مجرد غيض من فيض الحمض النووي.
Let me show you what you could do right now.
واسمحوا لي أبين لكم ما يمكن أن تفعلوه الآن.
A biohacker in Germany, a journalist, wanted to know
بيوهاكير في ألمانيا، صحفي، يريد أن يعرف
whose dog was leaving little presents on his street?
لمن الكلب الذي قام بترك هدايا في شارعه؟
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
Yep, you guessed it. He threw tennis balls
نعم، لقد حزرتم . لقد رمى كرات التنس
to all the neighborhood dogs, analyzed the saliva,
إلى جميع الكلاب الحي، بتحليل اللعاب،
identified the dog, and confronted the dog owner.
التعرف على الكلب، ومواجهة صاحب الكلب.
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
I discovered an invasive species in my own backyard.
اكتشفت فصيلة اجتاحت الفناء الخلفي الخاص بي.
Looked like a ladybug, right?
تشبه الخنفساء، حقيقة؟
It actually is a Japanese beetle.
في الواقع هي خنفساء اليابانية.
And the same kind of technology --
ونفس النوع من التكنولوجيا-
it's called DNA barcoding, it's really cool --
تسمى بتوازي الحمض النووي، وأنها حقاً رائعة-
You can use it to check if your caviar is really beluga,
يمكنك استخدامها لمعرفة ما إذا كان الكافيار الخاص بك هو حقاً لدلفين أبيض،
if that sushi is really tuna, or if that goat cheese
إذا كان حقاً أن السوشي بالتونة، أو أن ذلك كان جبنا الماعز
that you paid so much for is really goat's.
ستكون قد دفعت الكثير لتحصل على ذلك.
In a biohacker space, you can analyze your genome
في مساحة بيوهاكير، يمكنك تحليل الجينوم الخاص بك
for mutations.
للطفرات.
You can analyze your breakfast cereal for GMO's,
يمكنك تحليل حبوب الإفطار الخاصة بك من الكائنات المعدلة وراثيا،
and you can explore your ancestry.
ويمكنك استكشاف النسب الخاصة بك.
You can send weather balloons up into the stratosphere,
يمكنك إرسال بالونات الطقس إلى طبقة الستراتوسفير،
collect microbes, see what's up there.
جمع الميكروبات، ومعرفة ما يحصل هناك.
You can make a biocensor out of yeast
يمكنك أن تعزل البيوسينسور من الخميرة
to detect pollutants in water.
الكشف عن الملوثات في المياه.
You can make some sort of a biofuel cell.
يمكنك صنع نوعا من خلايا الوقود الحيوي.
You can do a lot of things.
يمكنك القيام بالكثير من الأشياء.
You can also do an art science project. Some of these
يمكنك أيضا القيام بمشروع علوم فني. والبعض من هذه
are really spectacular, and they look at social,
هي حقاً مذهلة، وتهم المجتمع،
ecological problems from a completely different perspective.
المشاكل البيئية من منظور مختلف تماما.
It's really cool.
أنها حقاً رائعة.
Some people ask me, well, why am I involved?
بعض الناس تسألني، حسنا، لماذا أنا مشتركة؟
I could have a perfectly good career in mainstream science.
يمكن أن تكون لي مسيرة عملية جيدة في العلم.
The thing is, there's something in these labs
الحقيقة أن هنالك أمر في هذه المختبرات
that they have to offer society that you can't find
حيث أنه يجب عليهم تقديم ما يصلون إليه إلى المجتمع
anywhere else.
في أي مكان آخر.
There's something sacred about a space where
هناك أمر مقدس حول المكان الذي
you can work on a project, and you don't have to justify
يمكنك العمل على مشروع دون الحاجة إلى تبرير
to anyone that it's going to make a lot of money,
لأي شخص أنه سيجنى الكثير من المال،
that it's going to save mankind, or even that it's feasible.
أنه سينقذ البشرية، أو حتى أنه ذلك ممكن .
It just has to follow safety guidelines.
يجب فقط أن تتبع إرشادات السلامة.
If you had spaces like this all over the world,
إذا كان لديك مساحة مماثلة هذا في جميع أنحاء العالم،
it could really change the perception
ستغير حقا تصوّر
of who's allowed to do biotech.
أؤلئك الذين قد يُسمح لهم القيام بالتكنولوجيا الحيوية.
It's spaces like these that spawned personal computing.
إنها مساحة مماثلة للتي انبثقت منها الحواسيب الشخصية.
Why not personal biotech?
لم لا التكنولوجيا الحيوية الشخصية؟
If everyone in this room got involved,
إذا كان كل شخص في هذه الغرفة اشترك،
who knows what we could do?
ومن يدري ماذا يمكن أن نفعل؟
This is such a new area, and as we say back in Brooklyn,
هذا مجال جديد، وكما نقول في بروكلين،
you ain't seen nothin' yet. (Laughter)
لم تشاهدوا شيئا بعد . (ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)